<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lake on Kelly Loria</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/lake/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Lake on Kelly Loria</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/lake/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Upstream efficiency and downstream productivity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity-the-influence-of-mountain-streamflow-on-nearshore-metabolism-in-a-large-oligotrophic-lake-across-drought-and-wet-years&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upstream efficiency and downstream productivity:&lt;/strong&gt; The influence of mountain streamflow on nearshore metabolism in a large, oligotrophic lake across drought and wet years.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;  &lt;p class=&#34;speshal-fancy-custom&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;  &lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; justify-content: space-between;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lake1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Your Image Alt Text&#34; style=&#34;max-width:45%; height:; auto;margin-right: 1%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/GBNS3_miniDOT.png&#34; alt=&#34;Your Image Alt Text&#34; style=&#34;max-width:40%; height:; auto;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Current warming trends and the expected variability in the timing and intensity of precipitation in mountain regions could also alter the availability of key resources and as well as physical processes, with unknown effects on downstream ecosystem energy fluxes (i.e., primary productivity - GPP and ecosystem respiration - ER). Therefore, we set out to characterize seasonal rates of productivity along the nearshore of Lake Tahoe across multiple catchments that accumulate different amounts of precipitation and have unique flow regimes for three consecutive and extreme hydroclimatic years (2021 to 2023).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Declines in alpine lake ice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/declines-in-alpine-lake-ice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/declines-in-alpine-lake-ice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-thin-ice-linking-elevation-and-long-term-losses-of-lake-ice-cover&#34;&gt;On thin ice: Linking elevation and long-term losses of lake ice cover&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Climate change is expected to have particularly strong effects in colder regions, such as those at high elevations. Yet due to remote locations and sparse data, it is unknown how mountain lakes are actually changing compared to other lakes in other regions. By assessing ice phenology trends for one of the highest (&amp;gt; 3000 m) and longest-running (36 yr) datasets on mountain lakes, we find that alpine lakes are decreasing ice cover 50% faster than average for more well-studied lakes in the Northern Hemisphere, emphasizing the importance of studying mountain lakes that provide water to nearly half of the world’s population. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://portal.edirepository.org/nis/mapbrowse?packageid=knb-lter-nwt.106.6&#34;&gt;Link to datasets&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-term apline zooplankton population dynamics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/long-term-apline-zooplankton-population-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/long-term-apline-zooplankton-population-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;phenology-of-alpine-zooplankton-populations-and-the-importance-of-lake-ice-out&#34;&gt;Phenology of alpine zooplankton populations and the importance of lake ice-out&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The prolonged ice cover inherent to alpine lakes incurs unique challenges for aquatic life, which are compounded by recent shifts in the timing and duration of ice cover. To understand the responses of alpine zooplankton, we analyzed a decade (2009–2019) of open-water samples of Daphnia pulicaria and Hesperodiaptomus shoshone for growth, reproduction and ultraviolet radiation tolerance (&lt;a href=&#34;https://portal.edirepository.org/nis/mapbrowse?scope=knb-lter-nwt&amp;amp;identifier=161&#34;&gt;Link to datasets&lt;/a&gt;). We described seasonal demographic patterns of growth, reproduction and trait expression for two common high elevation taxa Hesperodiaptomus shoshone and  Daphnia pulicaria. Throughout the course of our analysis, we observed large variation in ice cover, in particular the open water season ranged from 82 to 134 days. We found that both H. shoshone and D. pulicaria population dynamics were strongly related to water temperature, and were sensitive to the timing of lake ice clearance. Specifically we found that D. pulicaria biomass and melanization tended to be lowest immediately following ice clearance; whereas fecundity was relatively high. As the summer advanced D. pulicaria biomass and melanization linearly increased, while fecundity decreased. For example, 25% (standard deviation = 22%) of adult D. pulicaria were fecund within 20 days of ice clearance, and we observed lower rates of  fecundity (14-16%) for the remained of the open water season. In contrast, demographic patterns for H. shoshone tended to be non-linear, with peaks in biomass and fecundity around 30 to 40 days after ice-off, respectively, and we observed less variability in both metrics throughout the open water season relative to D. pulicaria. These findings will help inform future development of climate predictions for how high elevation aquatic communities are organized by providing patterns of seasonal population dynamics in natural systems and could aid in the development of a framework for how future predictions for reduced ice-cover could impact mountain lake communities across greater trophic scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative ecological characteristics of alpine lakes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/comparative-ecological-characteristics-of-alpine-lakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/comparative-ecological-characteristics-of-alpine-lakes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-life-aquatic-in-high-relief-shifts-in-the-physical-and-biological-characteristics-of-alpine-lakes-along-an-elevation-gradient-in-the-rocky-mountains-usa&#34;&gt;The life aquatic in high relief: shifts in the physical and biological characteristics of alpine lakes along an elevation gradient in the Rocky Mountains, USA&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 2016 I lead a survey of mountain lakes  ranging from 2480 to 3550 m a.s.l. in the Rocky Mountains of Colorado, USA. to investigate differences in ecological proccesses associated with landscape position.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;  &lt;p class=&#34;speshal-fancy-custom&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;  &lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; justify-content: space-between;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/Comp_lakes_snowbank.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Your Image Alt Text&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 60%; height: auto;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Employing a mixed modeling framework, we uncovered noteworthy associations between elevation and nearly all measured physiochemical parameters affecting water quality. These patterns appear to be driven by the pronounced changes in climate, terrestrial inputs, and atmospheric deposition that vary substantially with altitude. Expanding our analysis to biological communities, we found compelling evidence supporting elevation as a niche filter, with gamma diversity markedly lower (46%) for lakes situated above the treeline.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
