<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tahoe on Kelly Loria</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/tahoe/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tahoe on Kelly Loria</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/tahoe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Nitrogen availability and mountain stream metabolism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>Biogeochemical linkages between nitrogen availability and mountain stream metabolism I’m examining the temporal synchrony of nitrogen supply-demand relationships across multiple reaches and mountain catchments to evaluate how shifts in nitrogen supply-demand relationships may affect in-stream ecological processes in streams like algal abundance and stream metabolism.&#xA;Preliminary results suggest uptake length increased with nitrate supply and decreased with epilithic algal biomass. Uptake rates appear to increased with nitrate supply and surprisingly decreased with epilithic algal biomass.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upstream efficiency and downstream productivity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity/</guid>
      <description>Upstream efficiency and downstream productivity: The influence of mountain streamflow on nearshore metabolism in a large, oligotrophic lake across dry and wet years. Streams transform and transport materials and nutrients based on the availability of organic matter, woody debris1, sediment1, and watershed attributes such as land use2, residence time, hydrologic connectivity, and catchment size3,4 and are indicative of large-scale ecosystem change5. Current warming trends and the expected variability in the timing and intensity of precipitation in mountain regions could also alter the availability of key resources and as well as physical processes, with unknown effects on ecosystem energy fluxes (i.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
