<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tahoe on Kelly Loria</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/tahoe/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tahoe on Kelly Loria</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/tahoe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Nitrogen availability and mountain stream metabolism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>Biogeochemical linkages between nitrogen availability and mountain stream metabolism I’m examining the temporal synchrony of nitrogen supply-demand relationships across multiple reaches and mountain catchments to evaluate how shifts in nitrogen supply-demand relationships may affect in-stream ecological processes in streams like algal abundance and stream metabolism.&#xA;Preliminary results suggest uptake length increased with nitrate supply and decreased with epilithic algal biomass. Uptake rates appear to increased with nitrate supply and surprisingly decreased with epilithic algal biomass.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upstream efficiency and downstream productivity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity/</guid>
      <description>Upstream efficiency and downstream productivity: Linking mountain stream processes with near-shore productivity in the Lake Tahoe Basin. Upland processes (snowmelt, streamflow, and stream temperature) can influence littoral (nearshore) productivity dynamics through modulating the timing and delivery of materials to lakes. The degree to which upland processes influence nearshore productivity as a function of their catchment characteristics relative to the influence of internal lake processes remains unclear. We continuously monitored dissolved oxygen, temperature, and specific conductance (SPC) at different depths in the nearshore of Lake Tahoe CA/NV, USA and at the outlets of two watersheds with differing flow regimes for three consecutive years.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
