<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hydrology on Kelly Loria</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/hydrology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hydrology on Kelly Loria</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/hydrology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mountain stream ecosystem metabolism and nitrogen cycling responses to hydroclimatic volatility</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/mountain-stream-ecosystem-metabolism-and-nitrogen-cycling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/mountain-stream-ecosystem-metabolism-and-nitrogen-cycling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;biogeochemical-linkages-between-nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism&#34;&gt;Biogeochemical linkages between nitrogen availability and mountain stream metabolism&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p class=&#34;speshal-fancy-custom&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; justify-content: center;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;figure style=&#34;max-width: 80%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/BWU_algea1.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Algae at Blackwood Creek&#34; style=&#34;width: 100%; height: auto;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;figcaption style=&#34;font-size: 12px; margin-top: 0.5rem; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      Algae at Blackwood Creek, upper station location in September 2021.&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This project investigates how variability in snowpack accumulation alters the synchrony of hydrologic processes (e.g., peak flow, and the onset of baseflow) and biological processes (e.g., nutrient uptake, assimilation, and fixation) that control nitrogen availability and demand in two mountain streams. By comparing two streams that represent opposite ends of the spectrum in watershed size, modeled runoff, and precipitation accumulation within the Lake Tahoe basin (Nevada/California USA) over dry and wet years, we found the larger less shaded stream supported higher metabolism fluxes and exhibited more efficient inorganic nitrogen (e.g., nitrate and ammonium) assimilation. However, nitrogen assimilation and retention were severely reduced during the wet year due to the delayed onset of baseflow, which caused most available nitrogen in either stream to be transported instead of transformed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
