<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Biogeochemistry on Kelly Loria</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/biogeochemistry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Biogeochemistry on Kelly Loria</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/biogeochemistry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mountain streamflow and nearshore metabolism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/mountain-streamflow-and-nearshore-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/mountain-streamflow-and-nearshore-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-influence-of-mountain-streamflow-on-nearshore-metabolism-in-a-large-oligotrophic-lake-across-drought-and-wet-years&#34;&gt;The influence of mountain streamflow on nearshore metabolism in a large, oligotrophic lake across drought and wet years.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; justify-content: space-between; flex-wrap: wrap; gap: 1%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;  &lt;!-- Panel 1 --&gt;&#xA;  &lt;div style=&#34;flex: 1 1 30%; max-width: 38%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lake1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lake view&#34; style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 250px; object-fit: cover;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;figcaption style=&#34;font-size: 12px; margin-top: 0.5rem;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      Shoreline at Blackwood Creek in March 2022. &#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;  &lt;!-- Panel 2 --&gt;&#xA;  &lt;div style=&#34;flex: 1 1 30%; max-width: 38%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/GBNS3_miniDOT.png&#34; alt=&#34;Monitoring equipment&#34; style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 250px; object-fit: cover;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;figcaption style=&#34;font-size: 12px; margin-top: 0.5rem;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      Dive picture of the deeper littoral network near Blackwood Creek. &#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;  &lt;!-- Panel 3 --&gt;&#xA;  &lt;div style=&#34;flex: 1 1 30%; max-width: 25%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/Dive_Photo1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Dive Photo&#34; style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 250px; object-fit: cover;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;figcaption style=&#34;font-size: 12px; margin-top: 0.5rem;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      Dive picture of the deeper littoral network near Blackwood Creek. &#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This work examines how streamflow influences nearshore productivity in Lake Tahoe under contrasting wet and dry years, focusing on shorelines with varying inflow levels. By evaluating streamflow for shores with large, small, or no stream inflows (four locations across two shores) during two contrasting water years (one drought and one wet), this work showed how streamflow reduces water temperature, light availability, to indirectly influence nearshore metabolism in ways that varied with inflow size.  This work underscores how oligotrophic littoral productivity varies across shorelines and in response to hydrological conditions, with streamflow and precipitation exerting contrasting effects on metabolism depending on the proximity to inflowing streams.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mountain stream ecosystem metabolism and nitrogen cycling responses to hydroclimatic volatility</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/mountain-stream-ecosystem-metabolism-and-nitrogen-cycling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/mountain-stream-ecosystem-metabolism-and-nitrogen-cycling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;biogeochemical-linkages-between-nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism&#34;&gt;Biogeochemical linkages between nitrogen availability and mountain stream metabolism&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p class=&#34;speshal-fancy-custom&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; justify-content: center;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;figure style=&#34;max-width: 80%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/BWU_algea1.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Algae at Blackwood Creek&#34; style=&#34;width: 100%; height: auto;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;figcaption style=&#34;font-size: 12px; margin-top: 0.5rem; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      Algae at Blackwood Creek, upper station location in September 2021.&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This project investigates how variability in snowpack accumulation alters the synchrony of hydrologic processes (e.g., peak flow, and the onset of baseflow) and biological processes (e.g., nutrient uptake, assimilation, and fixation) that control nitrogen availability and demand in two mountain streams. By comparing two streams that represent opposite ends of the spectrum in watershed size, modeled runoff, and precipitation accumulation within the Lake Tahoe basin (Nevada/California USA) over dry and wet years, we found the larger less shaded stream supported higher metabolism fluxes and exhibited more efficient inorganic nitrogen (e.g., nitrate and ammonium) assimilation. However, nitrogen assimilation and retention were severely reduced during the wet year due to the delayed onset of baseflow, which caused most available nitrogen in either stream to be transported instead of transformed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-term apline zooplankton population dynamics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/long-term-apline-zooplankton-population-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/long-term-apline-zooplankton-population-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;phenology-of-alpine-zooplankton-populations-and-the-importance-of-lake-ice-out&#34;&gt;Phenology of alpine zooplankton populations and the importance of lake ice-out&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The prolonged ice cover inherent to alpine lakes incurs unique challenges for aquatic life, which are compounded by recent shifts in the timing and duration of ice cover. To understand the responses of alpine zooplankton, we analyzed a decade (2009–2019) of open-water samples of Daphnia pulicaria and Hesperodiaptomus shoshone for growth, reproduction and ultraviolet radiation tolerance (&lt;a href=&#34;https://portal.edirepository.org/nis/mapbrowse?scope=knb-lter-nwt&amp;amp;identifier=161&#34;&gt;Link to datasets&lt;/a&gt;). We described seasonal demographic patterns of growth, reproduction and trait expression for two common high elevation taxa Hesperodiaptomus shoshone and  Daphnia pulicaria. Throughout the course of our analysis, we observed large variation in ice cover, in particular the open water season ranged from 82 to 134 days. We found that both H. shoshone and D. pulicaria population dynamics were strongly related to water temperature, and were sensitive to the timing of lake ice clearance. Specifically we found that D. pulicaria biomass and melanization tended to be lowest immediately following ice clearance; whereas fecundity was relatively high. As the summer advanced D. pulicaria biomass and melanization linearly increased, while fecundity decreased. For example, 25% (standard deviation = 22%) of adult D. pulicaria were fecund within 20 days of ice clearance, and we observed lower rates of  fecundity (14-16%) for the remained of the open water season. In contrast, demographic patterns for H. shoshone tended to be non-linear, with peaks in biomass and fecundity around 30 to 40 days after ice-off, respectively, and we observed less variability in both metrics throughout the open water season relative to D. pulicaria. These findings will help inform future development of climate predictions for how high elevation aquatic communities are organized by providing patterns of seasonal population dynamics in natural systems and could aid in the development of a framework for how future predictions for reduced ice-cover could impact mountain lake communities across greater trophic scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
