<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Biogeochemistry on Kelly Loria</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/biogeochemistry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Biogeochemistry on Kelly Loria</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/biogeochemistry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Upstream efficiency and downstream productivity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;upstream-efficiency-and-downstream-productivity-the-influence-of-mountain-streamflow-on-nearshore-metabolism-in-a-large-oligotrophic-lake-across-drought-and-wet-years&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upstream efficiency and downstream productivity:&lt;/strong&gt; The influence of mountain streamflow on nearshore metabolism in a large, oligotrophic lake across drought and wet years.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;  &lt;p class=&#34;speshal-fancy-custom&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;  &lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; justify-content: space-between;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lake1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Your Image Alt Text&#34; style=&#34;max-width:45%; height:; auto;margin-right: 1%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/GBNS3_miniDOT.png&#34; alt=&#34;Your Image Alt Text&#34; style=&#34;max-width:40%; height:; auto;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Current warming trends and the expected variability in the timing and intensity of precipitation in mountain regions could also alter the availability of key resources and as well as physical processes, with unknown effects on downstream ecosystem energy fluxes (i.e., primary productivity - GPP and ecosystem respiration - ER). Therefore, we set out to characterize seasonal rates of productivity along the nearshore of Lake Tahoe across multiple catchments that accumulate different amounts of precipitation and have unique flow regimes for three consecutive and extreme hydroclimatic years (2021 to 2023).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nitrogen availability and mountain stream metabolism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;biogeochemical-linkages-between-nitrogen-availability-and-mountain-stream-metabolism&#34;&gt;Biogeochemical linkages between nitrogen availability and mountain stream metabolism&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’m examining the temporal synchrony of nitrogen supply-demand relationships across multiple reaches and mountain catchments to evaluate how shifts in nitrogen supply-demand relationships may affect in-stream ecological processes in streams like algal abundance and stream metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;  &lt;p class=&#34;speshal-fancy-custom&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;  &lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; justify-content: space-between;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/NCycle_diagram.png&#34; alt=&#34;Your Image Alt Text&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 60%; height: auto;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Preliminary results suggest uptake length increased with nitrate supply and decreased with epilithic algal biomass. Uptake rates appear to increased with nitrate supply and surprisingly decreased with epilithic algal biomass. These results could suggest that summertime epilithic algal biomass is not necessarily limited by nitrate supply and is instead more governed by environmental forcing (water temperature and flow).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-term apline zooplankton population dynamics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/long-term-apline-zooplankton-population-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/long-term-apline-zooplankton-population-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;phenology-of-alpine-zooplankton-populations-and-the-importance-of-lake-ice-out&#34;&gt;Phenology of alpine zooplankton populations and the importance of lake ice-out&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The prolonged ice cover inherent to alpine lakes incurs unique challenges for aquatic life, which are compounded by recent shifts in the timing and duration of ice cover. To understand the responses of alpine zooplankton, we analyzed a decade (2009–2019) of open-water samples of Daphnia pulicaria and Hesperodiaptomus shoshone for growth, reproduction and ultraviolet radiation tolerance (&lt;a href=&#34;https://portal.edirepository.org/nis/mapbrowse?scope=knb-lter-nwt&amp;amp;identifier=161&#34;&gt;Link to datasets&lt;/a&gt;). We described seasonal demographic patterns of growth, reproduction and trait expression for two common high elevation taxa Hesperodiaptomus shoshone and  Daphnia pulicaria. Throughout the course of our analysis, we observed large variation in ice cover, in particular the open water season ranged from 82 to 134 days. We found that both H. shoshone and D. pulicaria population dynamics were strongly related to water temperature, and were sensitive to the timing of lake ice clearance. Specifically we found that D. pulicaria biomass and melanization tended to be lowest immediately following ice clearance; whereas fecundity was relatively high. As the summer advanced D. pulicaria biomass and melanization linearly increased, while fecundity decreased. For example, 25% (standard deviation = 22%) of adult D. pulicaria were fecund within 20 days of ice clearance, and we observed lower rates of  fecundity (14-16%) for the remained of the open water season. In contrast, demographic patterns for H. shoshone tended to be non-linear, with peaks in biomass and fecundity around 30 to 40 days after ice-off, respectively, and we observed less variability in both metrics throughout the open water season relative to D. pulicaria. These findings will help inform future development of climate predictions for how high elevation aquatic communities are organized by providing patterns of seasonal population dynamics in natural systems and could aid in the development of a framework for how future predictions for reduced ice-cover could impact mountain lake communities across greater trophic scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
